原视频名：Richard Branson Tries To Beat Jeff Bezos To Space,
But Jeff's Final Passenger Is Amazing Choice
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/0b1VgtyIQN0
原视频发布日期：20210703
字幕翻译：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
It's been an eventful couple of days
最近大事连连
for Virgin Galactic and Blue Origin and they are competition for commercial suborbital tourist flights.
对于维珍银河和蓝色起源及其在商业亚轨道旅游飞行方面的竞争来说
But before I get to that
但在我谈这个问题之前
I want to congratulate Virgin Orbit the sister company of Virgin Galactic
我想祝贺维珍轨道公司 也就是维珍银河的姐妹公司
for their first commercial flight where they carried four cubesats into orbit.
第一次商业飞行(的成功) 在这次飞行中将四颗立方星送入了轨道
So this was using their LauncherOne vehicle
那么这次发射使用的是发射器一号
which is carried under Cosmic Girl which is a refurbished 747.
由宇宙女孩这个翻新的波音747携带
They took off from Mojave air and spaceport flew out over the pacific did a test run
他们从莫哈韦航空航天港起飞 飞到太平洋上空 进行了一次试运行
and then launched their rocket and we got to see this during a live stream.
然后发射他们的火箭 我们在直播中看到了发射
So immediately after launch we got to look back at the rocket
因此 在发射后 我们立刻回想起这枚火箭
and it did have this problem that we saw previously
确实还有以前见过的问题
where there were some roll oscillations early in the flight.
也就是飞行初期有一些滚转振荡
Having said that it seems that we didn't see any of the oscillations later on
尽管如此 之后我们似乎就没有看到任何振荡了
so they've certainly improved that situation.
所以他们肯定已经改善了这种情况
The vehicle made it all the way to orbit
航天器成功入轨
and they also demonstrated relight of the main engines in orbit
同时还验证了在轨道上重新点火主发动机的过程
which is a really good feature to have
这是一个非常好的功能
so Virgin Orbit are going to have at least another few launches.
那么维珍轨道将至少再进行几次发射
They already have another few launches on the calendar
他们已经在日程表上安排了另外几次发射
and I hope to see more.
而我希望能看到更多
But coming back to the main account.
但话归正题
Well I woke up one day to see the news on Jeff Bezos's instagram
有一天 我醒来看到杰夫·贝佐斯的Instagram上的新闻
that Wally Funk was going to fly on the first flight of Blue Origin's New Shepard.
沃利·冯克将参加蓝色起源的新谢泼德号的首次(载人)飞行
And yeah you may not have heard of Wally Funk but I have.
是的 你可能没有听说过沃利·冯克 但我听说过
Her real name is Mary Wallace Funk shortened to Wally Funk
她的真名是玛丽·华莱士·冯克 简称为沃利·冯克
and I guess she's one of the Mercury 13
那么我认为她是水星13号中的一员
and I'm using finger quotes because Mercury 13 was really a sort of media creation.
而我用手指引号是因为水星13号确实是一种媒体创造
Basically this is a group of 13 women.
基本上这是由13名妇女组成的团体
The doctor who did all the medical tests for the Mercury 7, the original and seven american astronauts.
为水星七号 即最初的七名美国宇航员做所有医疗测试的医生
He wanted to see if women were able to do this
想看看女性是否能够做到这一点
so he got a bunch of women pilots together
所以他把一群女飞行员召集起来
and filtered them down and they ended up with 13 of them who passed all the first round tests.
并对她们进行了筛选 最后有13人通过了所有第一轮测试
Some of them better than the astronauts.
其中一些人比宇航员还要好
Let's be clear. Better than the male astronauts.
让我们把话说清楚 比男性宇航员更好
And Wally Funk she was one of the few
而沃利·冯克是少数几个
I think maybe the only one that actually completed all three rounds of the testing
我想也许是唯一一个真正完成所有三轮测试的人
and also demonstrated better results than some of the astronauts that were flying in space.
而且比起一些在太空飞行的宇航员 她还做到了更好的结果
Because this program was not official
因为这个项目不是官方的
NASA actually started to become hostile to it
NASA实际上开始变得对它有敌意
and they stopped them using NASA facilities at one point
而且一度阻止他们使用NASA的设施
so they had to come up with alternatives to do this
所以他们不得不想出其他办法来做这件事
but yeah long story short she tried to fly to space in the 1960s
但是 是的 长话短说 她在1960年代试图飞向太空
and NASA pushed back against
而NASA对其进行了阻挠
and their main justification was that they absolutely had to have jet pilot experience
而他们的主要理由是 宇航员必须有喷气机飞行员的经验
and that was practically impossible for women to get
而这对女性来说几乎是不可能的
because they weren't allowed in the air force.
因为她们不被允许在空军服役
Famously in the 1960s or 1950s actually
事实上 著名的是在20世纪60年代或50年代
I think it was Jacqueline Cochran wanted
我觉得是杰奎琳·考克伦想要
she was like a famous woman pilot.
她是一个著名的女飞行员
She wanted to set the air speed record for women.
想要创造女性的飞行速度记录
And she's an american citizen so what does she do?
而她是一个美国公民 那么她做了什么？
She goes to the US air force
她去找美国空军
and says could I borrow one of your F-86s
说我能不能借你们的F-86战斗机一用？
and they said no.
而他们说不行
So she went to Canada and said could I borrow one of yours.
于是她去找加拿大 说我能不能借你们的一架
And they said sure because Canada's cool
而他们说当然可以 因为加拿大很酷
and they're not weird like the US was.
而且他们并不像美国那样古怪
And yes she set the records and everything.
是的 她创造了记录 并做到了一切
Now she would actually then be sort of one of the proponents or for the Mercury 13
那么 实际上她是水星13号的支持者之一
although she originally had the idea that she might fly to space
虽然最初她的想法是也许她可以飞向太空
and it became clear that she was kind of too old by that point.
但很明显 (在水星13号计划的时候)她已经太老了
But yeah ultimately there's a moment
但是 是的 终于有一刻
where there's a letter that gets drafted by someone at the white house
白宫有人起草了一封信
to NASA to ask about this jet requirement
向NASA询问关于这个喷气机的要求
and it makes it the desk of Lyndon B. Johnson
而它到了林登·B·约翰逊的桌上
and he just writes "let's stop this now" over it.
而他只是在上面写了 让我们现在就停止这一切
And yeah it never happened.
但是 是的 这从未发生过
So now 2021 she is gonna fly for a few minutes to space finally and that's fantastic.
因此 现在是2021年 她终于要飞到太空几分钟了 这真是太棒了
I think it shows that Jeff Bezos actually has an awareness of space history
我认为这表明 杰夫·贝索斯实际上对太空历史有一点了解
that perhaps maybe Elon or Richard Branson maybe don't have.
也许马一龙或者理查德·布兰森就没有
But yeah when she flies for the moment that she's in space
但是 是的 当她在太空中飞行的那一刻
she will be the most experienced pilot in space.
她将是太空中最有经验的飞行员
Think about that she has 19600 pilot hours.
想想看 她有19600个飞行小时
She has been a flight instructor forever.
她一直是一个飞行教官
She's worked with the National Transportation Safety Board.
她曾与国家运输安全委员会(NTSB)合作
They worked with FAA and all sorts of like
他们与美国联邦航空局合作 以及各种各样的像
basically if you look at her wikipedia page
基本上 如果你看一下她的维基百科页面
you'll see all the different roles that she ended up with in.
你会看到她参与过的各种不同的角色
And most of those end up saying she was the first woman to do this.
而大多数条目最后都说她是第一个做这个的女性
So look obviously an amazingly qualified individual.
那么你看 显然她是一位极度优秀的人
One whose time is definitely overdue.
尽管她的时代肯定已经过去了
When she flies she will be 82.
当她参与这次飞行时 她将是82岁
She will be the oldest person to ever fly in space
会是有史以来在太空飞行的最年长的人
and I hope that I am as capable and as bright at 82 as she is.
而我希望我在82岁时也能像她一样有能 一样聪明
I think this is amazing.
我认为这很了不起
So that's gonna fly on July 20th.
所以这将在7月20日飞行
A few hours after that announcement Virgin Galactic made an announcement.
在这一声明的几个小时后 维珍银河发表了一项声明
They released a slick video saying we're gonna fly our first full flight of SpaceShipTwo
他们发布了一个华丽的视频 表明太空船二号的首次完整飞行
with two pilots and four mission specialists
有两名飞行员和四名任务专家
And among those mission specialists there will be Richard Branson
而在这些任务专家中 会有理查德·布兰森
so yes that's going to be on July 11th
那么是的 那将是在7月11日
so that's nine days before the flight date of Blue Origin's New Shepard.
那么这比蓝色起源的新谢泼德的飞行日期早了9天
Richard Branson just wanted to make sure he's first.
理查德·布兰森只是想确保他是第一个(进行商业亚轨道飞行)
The Blue Origin flight that's going to be Jeff Bezos, his brother
蓝色起源的飞行(乘员)将包括杰夫·贝佐斯和他的弟弟
unknown paid passenger by the way we don't know and Wally Funk.
未知的付款乘客 以及沃利·冯克
so that's four people.
那么 这是四个人
But the Virgin Galactic flight that will have Dave Mackay and Michael Masucci as the pilots
但维珍银河的飞行乘员为戴夫·麦基和迈克尔·马祖奇作为飞行员
and then they will have Beth Moses who's previously flown on this.
然后则是贝丝·摩西 她以前曾在这上面飞行过
She'll be acting as a trainer or whatever.
她将充当培训师之类的角色
She's basically in charge of the crew training or passenger training.
她基本上负责机组人员培训或者说乘客培训
They're going to have Colin Bennett who's their lead operations engineer
还有科林·本尼特 他是太空船二号的首席操作工程师
and Sirisha Bandla who's basically
和西莉莎·班德拉 她基本上是
she is like Virgin Galactic's vp of government contracts and research and stuff
维珍银河负责政府合同和研究等的副总裁
and so she'll actually be performing a scientific experiment for the university of Florida during the flight
所以她实际上将在飞行期间为佛罗里达大学进行科学实验
and then of course rounding out the mission specialists you have Richard Branson
当然还有理查德·布兰森
who's evaluating the customer experience.
他会评估客户体验
Of course he is.
不愧是他
So like the thing is we sort of knew this was coming.
因此 事情是这样的 我们知道这将会发生
We knew that this was a possibility right.
我们知道这是一种可能性 对吧
But nobody would say it out loud until this week.
但直到本周 没有人愿意大声说出来
So it hasn't exactly come as a surprise
所以它并不完全是一个惊喜
but equally it was kind of interesting to see
但同样 看到这一点也很有趣
this happening on the same day as these two announcements.
这两个声明发生在同一天
Okay so these are two very different vehicles.
好吧 这是两种非常不同的交通工具
Virgin Galactic has SpaceShipTwo
维珍银河的太空船二号
which is a rocket-powered aircraft dropped from a carrier aircraft.
是一个以火箭为动力的飞机 从其运载飞机上投掷下来
Blue Origin has New Shepard
蓝色起源有新谢泼德
which is a single stage hydrogen-powered rocket
这是一个单级液氢动力的火箭
with a crew capsule on top that lands under parachutes.
上面有一个乘员舱 其使用降落伞降落
So they both offer different things.
那么他们的飞行是截然不同的
I think actually in some ways New Shepard the views are more amazing
我认为 实际上在某些方面 新谢泼德的景色更令人惊叹
because you've got these much bigger windows and it goes slightly higher.
因为你有这些大得多的窗户 而且它的高度略高
Virgin Galactic SpaceShipTwo is a plane and it does cool stuff
维珍银河的太空船二号是一架飞机 它能做一些很酷的事情
and it's actually flown by a person at the controls
而且它实际上是由一个人控制着飞行的
and it has this big hybrid rocket motor
而且它有这种大型的(固液)混合火箭发动机
where it's basically like full any solid casing
它基本上是一个完整的固体外壳
and then they blow hot nitrous oxide down it
然后用热的一氧化二氮吹向它
and that causes a rocket thrust or whatever and they fly it upwards.
这样的氧化反应产生火箭推力 然后他们把它向上飞
There's a pair of pilots flying at these controls
有一对飞行员使用这些控制器
and they fly at speeds greater than mach 3.
而且他们会以大于3马赫的速度飞行
And this is actually an old-school type control system with reversible controls.
而这实际上是一个老式的操纵系统 也就是可逆操纵系统
There are actually cables that link those controls to the things.
实际上 操纵面直接由钢缆连接
There's no fly-by-wire system or anything here.
没有电传操纵的部分
And that's something you generally don't see.
而这是很罕见的
Supersonic aircraft with reversible controls.
也就是带有可逆操纵装置的超音速飞机
No fly-by-wire systems or anything to get in the way.
这个系统中并不包括电传操纵
What will happen is it pulls up into this climb after launch
将会发生的是它在发射后拉升到这个爬升状态
and as the engine shuts off and it starts to get to the thinner parts of the atmosphere.
而当发动机关闭时 它开始进入大气层的较薄部分
It then folds its tail planes into a vertical orientation
然后把它的尾翼折叠到垂直的方向
so that when it comes back down the belly of the aircraft is pointing straight down
所以当它回来的时候 飞机的腹部是直直地朝下的
and that is decelerating the spacecraft through the thinner parts of the atmosphere.
而这就使航天器能在大气层的较薄部分减速
so that they get subsonic once they get to thicker parts of the atmosphere.
这样 一旦进入大气层较厚的部分 就能减速到亚音速
If you did this with a regular aircraft like the X-15
如果对于X-15这种的普通飞机这样做的话
it went up and then when it came back down
它升空了 然后当它回落时
it would be like a lawn dart and they had to pull this thing out of this dive.
就像一个草地上的飞镖 而且必须从这个俯冲中拉出来
and that was obviously quite an extreme experience.
而这显然是一个相当极端的感受
so yeah New Shepard as I said they have this single stage rocket.
那么 是的 正如我所说 新谢泼德是单级火箭
They use a hydrogen engine which is kind of interesting
他们使用的是液氢发动机 这有点儿意思
because it's more expensive to work with hydrogen.
因为使用液氢的成本更高
But also I think this is the first vehicle
但我也认为这是第一个这样的航天器
that's really had a large number of flights that uses a combustion tap-off cycle.
也就是使用了抽气循环的发动机进行过大量实际的飞行
That's where the turbo pumps instead of having a separate gas generator
抽气循环是指 涡轮泵不使用单独的气体发生器
they essentially have a pipe in the combustion chamber
而是基本上在燃烧室上开一个管道
that feeds into the turbo pumps and drives those
将废气输送到涡轮泵中并驱动它们
so it's a sort of simpler system but it's harder to balance in many ways.
那么这是一种更简单的系统 但它在许多方面更难平衡
The booster goes up
助推器上升
and once they cut that off they detach and the capsule proceeds upwards on its own trajectory.
之后 一旦关闭了助推器 就会脱离 而返回舱就会按自己的轨迹向上飞行
It reaches about 105 kilometers and then comes back down slowly
它会到达大约105千米 然后慢慢地回来
and lands on the desert with a parachute and a little rocket motor.
之后用一个降落伞和一个小火箭发动机降落在沙漠上
The booster it deploys air brakes and aerodynamic hardware.
它的助推器会展开阻力板和空气动力设备(翼面)
It comes down and it then lands on the landing pad using rocket motors.
降下来以后 再用火箭发动机降落在着陆场上
So that's a kind of a cool demonstration there.
那么 这是一种很酷的展示
Blue Origin are fond of saying that
蓝色起源很喜欢说
they were the first people to fly a rocket booster to space twice and come back.
它是第一个做到把火箭助推器飞到太空两次并回来的公司
And of course SpaceX response said yeah but you didn't go orbital
当然 SpaceX回应说 是的 但你没有进入轨道
and there's a little bit of this going on here
而且类似的东西也要如此发生
because Blue Origin are going to fly to 105 kilometers
因为蓝色起源要飞到105千米处
whereas Virgin Galactic are only going to fly to about 90 something kilometers.
而维珍银河只打算飞到大约90千米的地方
They're not going to exceed 100 kilometers
他们不打算超过100千米
and that actually is kind of a big deal
那么这实际上是一个大问题
because the international definition of space is about 100 kilometers.
因为国际上对太空的定义是大约100千米
That's the FAI that decided that.
这是由国际航空联合会决定的
However in the US the definition is 50 miles
然而在美国 定义是50英里(80.46千米)
which then subsequently has been rounded off to 80 kilometers.
随后被四舍五入为80千米
And a lot of this dates to an argument by Theodore von Kármán.
而这可以追溯到西奥多·冯·卡门的一个论点
They call this the Kármán line.
他们把这称为卡门线
And his argument is that space should begin
而他的论点是 太空的起点为
where the forces due to gravity and acceleration exceed the aerodynamic forces
重力的作用力 或者说加速度 超过了空气动力的作用力(或加速度)
that they would expect experience in these trajectories.
在这样的轨道上面
And what you do is you sort of figure out how fast you have to go just remain airborne
而你要做的是 你要计算出你必须走多快才能保持在空中飞行
and at a certain point between about 80 and 100 kilometers it flips over.
而在大约80到100千米之间的某个点上 这两者的作用就会对调
You basically says you have to be moving at orbital velocity to maintain lift.
你基本上说你必须以轨道速度移动以保持升力
And I think and this is where there's a little bit of history.
我想 这就是有一点历史的地方了
So the FAI decided to round that up to 100 kilometers.
所以FAI决定将其四舍五入为100千米
The US decided to round that to about 50 miles.
美国决定将其四舍五入到50英里左右
And there's actually a good argument that it should be about 50 miles.
实际上有一个很好的论点 那就是它应该是50英里左右
And the main argument is that
主要的论据是
we have seen many satellites in highly eccentric orbits that go out a long way
我们已经看到许多卫星在高度偏心的轨道上飞出很远的距离
and then they fall back down and they pass through the outer layers of the atmosphere
然后它们回落 穿过大气层的外层
and they're able to pass through below 100 kilometers many times
他们能够多次通过低于100千米的地方
but once they get below about 80 kilometers, they fall out of the sky very very quickly.
但一旦它们到达80千米以下 它们就会非常迅速地从天空中坠落
So from a sort of physics point of view
因此 从某种物理学的角度来看
the argument is that 80 kilometers makes a lot more sense.
80千米的论点更有意义
And Jonathan McDowell was one of the scientists who's really looked at this a whole lot.
而乔纳森·麦克道尔是真正研究过这个问题的科学家之一
So I'm actually okay with using this lower definition of space
因此 我实际上可以接受这种高度较低的太空定义
and yet it will be very cool when Virgin Galactic actually fly
然而 当维珍银河实际飞行时 这将是非常酷的
because they will have six people on board.
因为他们将有六个人在船上
And that means for a minute or so
而这意味着在一分钟左右的时间里
when they're above the Kármán line or their version of the Kármán line
当他们在卡门线 或者说他们版本的卡门线上方时
there will be six extra people in space.
将会有六个额外的人在太空中
There's currently 10 people in space.
目前有10个人在太空中
There's 3 in the Chinese Space Station.
中国空间站里有3人
4 flew up on a Dragon on the ISS
国际空间站里乘坐龙飞船升空的4人
and 3 that have flown up under Soyuz
还有乘坐联盟号升空的3人
so that's 10 plus 6.
因此 这是10个加6个
That will be 16 people in space.
这将是16人在太空中
That will be a record number of people in space for a very short time.
这将是非常短的时间内处在太空中的人数的记录
The current record is 13.
目前的记录是13人
Also so when Blue Origin's New Shepard flies
另外 当蓝色起源的新谢泼德号飞行时
if they somehow the schedule drifts or lags and Blue Origin get their first
如果维珍银河的飞行以某种方式推迟了 而蓝色起源先飞了
14 would also be a record number of people in space.
14人也将是太空中人数的一个记录
Speaking of records incidentally I sort of realized that the pilots for Virgin Galactic
说到记录 我有点意识到 维珍银河的飞行员们
they will be flying multiple trips to space.
将多次飞行到太空
And if they do this with any real cadence,
如果他们真的按照一定的频率进行太空飞行
it's quite possible that the at the pilots for Virgin Galactic
很有可能在维珍银河的飞行员中
will have the record number of space flights in a very short time
将在很短的时间内创下太空飞行次数的记录
and also talking about records
既然提到了记录
we have Wally Funk who's going to be the oldest astronaut ever.
沃利·冯克将成为有史以来年龄最大的宇航员
This year we'll also see the youngest american astronaut
而且今年我们还将看到最年轻的美国宇航员
as a Haley Arsenault is going to be 29 years old.
因为海莉·阿瑟诺上太空的时候 将年满29岁
In the Soviet Union they flew like Gagarin was 27.
在苏联 上太空的年轻人 比如加加林是27岁
Gherman Titov who is the record holder.
戈尔曼·季托夫是记录保持者
He was only 25
他当时只有25岁
and Valentina Tereshkova was 26.
而瓦莲京娜·捷列什科娃是26岁
But Haley Arsenault will be 29.
但是海莉·阿瑟诺将是29岁
She'll be the youngest astronaut
她将是(史上)最年轻的(美国)宇航员
and she'll spend several days in space.
而且会在太空中度过数天
One other thing that occurred to me was that
我想到的另一件事是
the up the fourth passenger on Blue Origin.
蓝色起源上的第四位乘客
They clearly paid a lot of money
他们显然付了很多钱
and part of that attraction was not just being first
而付很多钱的吸引力是 不仅仅能成为第一个(来自民间的商业航天客户)
but also getting to hang out with Jeff Bezos and talk about things.
而且还能和杰夫·贝佐斯一起玩耍 谈论一些事情
But you know what
但是你知道吗？
if I was on that flight I would be far more interested in talking to Wally Funk.
如果我在那枚火箭上 我会更有兴趣与沃利·冯克交谈
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manly 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]